[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Forty]
[第四十集]
dad
爸爸
How to speak of the devil
怎么说曹操曹操就到啊
What delicious food did you bring me, Dad?
爸爸 你给我带了什么好吃的
sesame candy
麻糖
How's it going? Have you seen Yannian and them?
怎么样 见到延年他们了吗
Hurry up and slow down
紧赶慢赶
Finally, they met before they set off.
总算是在他们出发前见了一面
that's good
那就好
Come into the house
来 进屋
Brother Zhongfu is at home, right?
仲甫兄在家吧
Director Wu
吴总监
Yes, madam.
夫人好
I'm Wu Bingxiang, director of the Metropolitan Police Department.
我是京师警察厅总监吴炳湘
Hello, Director Wu
吴总监好
Come into the house with your mother.
来 跟妈妈先进屋
My front foot just walked in the door.
我这前脚刚进门
The luggage hasn't been laid down yet.
行李还没放下呢
This hind foot followed you in.
您这后脚就跟着进来了
The efficiency of this metropolitan police department is really high.
这京师警察厅的效率可真高啊
Professor Chen, you left Beijing without permission.
陈教授 你擅自离京
Make so much noise in Wuhan
在武汉闹出那么大动静
Now I can return to Beijing safely.
如今能平安回京
I have to come to see you.
我不得不来看你呀
Director Wu is very kind.
吴总监太客气了
Professor Chen, we are fellow villagers.
陈教授 咱们可是老乡啊
Naturally, I should take more care of you.
我自然要对你多关照一些才是啊
Don't forget that I'm a sponsor when you get out of prison.
你别忘了 你出狱我可是保人
I'm involved.
担着干系呢
clear
明白
Director Wu
吴总监
Have a seat in the house.
屋里坐会儿吧
No, no, no
不了不了
He just came back.
他刚刚回来
Professor Chen
陈教授啊
conduct oneself well
好自为之
see you again
后会有期
good-bye
慢走
A policeman came to your house yesterday.
昨天就有警察到家里来找你了
You just walked in the door.
你前脚刚进门
This Wu Bingxiang followed me again.
这吴炳湘又跟过来了
Is something wrong?
是出什么情况了吗
They must have read it in the newspaper.
一定是他们看到了报纸上
Report on my speech in Wuhan
关于我在武汉演讲的报导
Don't open my luggage like this.
这样 我的行李别打开了
I'll go directly to Shizhi's place.
我直接去适之那儿
good
好
dodge
闪开
get out of the way
让开
Get out of the way
让开 让开
dodge
闪开
Shizhi
适之
respectful form of address for a male friend
兄长
Come in and warm up.
快 快进来 暖一暖
Brother Zhongfu, you're back.
仲甫兄 你回来了
Sister in law, do me a favor.
弟妹 你帮我一个忙
Go next door and call Gao Yihan for me.
你到隔壁去帮我叫一下高一涵
Tell him to call Shouchang Deqian.
让他把守常 德潜都叫过来
Better call Yucai, too.
[胡适 字 适之 北京大学教授]
Good boy, okay, okay, I'm going now
好好好 我现在就去
Brother Zhongfu, what happened?
仲甫兄 出什么事了
Call everyone in the cold weather.
来 大冷的天把大家都叫来
excuse me
打扰了
Sit quickly.
快坐
Call you all today.
今天把你们都叫来
I want you to help me analyze it.
是想请大家帮我分析一下
Should I leave Beijing?
我要不要离开北京
The situation I'm facing at the moment is rather urgent.
眼下我面临的情势比较紧迫
Jingshi Police Department
京师警察厅
There is a surveillance post at my door.
在我家门口设了监视岗
I just got home with my front foot.
我前脚刚到家
Wu Bingxiang came to warn me.
后脚吴炳湘就来警告我
Do not leave Beijing without permission.
不可擅自出京
That's obviously a thorn in my side.
那显然是把我当成眼中钉了
So it seems more troublesome.
这么看来比较麻烦
It's reasonable to go out and hide at this time.
按道理 这个时候应该出去躲躲
But I'm thinking if I do leave.
可是我在想 如果我真的走了
What about New Youth?
《新青年》怎么办
After all, it's not my business alone.
毕竟不是我一个人的事
This Wu Bingxiang is really not a thing
这吴炳湘真不是个东西
I say ignore him.
要我说 别理他
Is that why I'm going to arrest you again?
难道就因为这点事再把你抓进去
Don't you talk about the law?
还讲不讲法度了
Don't take it lightly.
不可掉以轻心
People like Wu Bingxiang
吴炳湘这种人
Anything can be done.
什么事情都做得出来
Don't expect him to tell you the truth.
千方别指望他跟你讲法度
Zhongfu, you don't care too much.
仲甫 你也是太不在意了
I read the Wuhan newspaper.
我看了武汉报纸上
The remarks that appeared in your speech
刊登了你的演讲的言论
Publicly publicize communism
公开地宣扬共产主义
And class struggle theory.
和阶级斗争学说
Also said to make what bloody revolution?
还说要搞什么流血革命
Cancel private ownership
取消私有制
These remarks are really out of line.
这些言论确实是出格了
the bird which takes the lead gets shot first―the person in the limelight bears the brunt of attack
枪打出头鸟
Why don't you always take lessons?
你怎么老是不接受教训呢
Shizhi, is it still meaningful to say this now?
适之 现在说这些还有意义吗
I say simply go to the south.
要我说 索性到南方去
Open your arms and have a big fight
甩开膀子大干一场
To the south.
去南方
Deported
被驱逐回来的
Shizhi, now we have to go to the south.
适之 我们现在只有到南方去
My talent
我才
Sorry, guys.
对不住 各位
I'm sorry
对不起
I got everyone involved.
是我连累了大家
Well, I think I'd better leave Beijing.
这样吧 我想我还是离开北京吧
Chinese New Year is coming soon.
马上快过年了
If I really have something
我要真有什么情况
Seven-step poems have spoiled everyone's interest.
岂不是扫了大家的兴
Brother Zhongfu, where are you going?
仲甫兄 你打算去哪儿啊
I am ready to accept the southern government.
我准备接受南方政府
Offer to prepare for Southwest University
筹办西南大学的聘书
I want to go to Shanghai first.
我想先去上海
The political environment there is better than that in Beijing.
那里的政治环境比北京要好
And the labor and business communities have come to their senses.
劳工和商界都已经觉悟了
Unlike Beijing, it's still stuffy in the student circle.
不像北京 还闷在学生圈子里
In addition, I also want to put New Youth
另外 我也想把《新青年》
Take it to Shanghai, too
也一块带到上海去
New Youth is in Beijing.
《新青年》在北京
Especially in Peking University.
特别是在北大
There is already a broad base.
已经有了广泛的基础
Why start a new stove?
何必舍近求远 另起炉灶
I agree with brother Zhongfu.
我同意仲甫兄的意见
The New Youth was brought by Zhongfu.
《新青年》是仲甫带来的
Naturally, I should follow you
自然应该跟着你
No, what's Chen Duxiu called "New Youth"
没有陈独秀叫什么《新青年》
No matter "New Youth"
无论《新青年》
Go anywhere.
走到任何一个地方
As long as brother Zhongfu has it.
只要还在仲甫兄手里
We will continue to support it.
我们就一如既往地支持
I agree
我同意
agree
同意
Thank you Yucai
谢谢豫才
Then it's settled.
那就这么定了
I will go to Shanghai by train tomorrow.
明天我坐火车去上海
After arriving in Shanghai
到上海之后
First, I'll ask Zhang Shizhao in the name of the southern government.
我先请章士钊以南方政府的名义
Send an official letter to the Metropolitan Police Department.
给京师警察厅发一个公函
Just tell him I've been hired as
就告诉他我已经被聘为
The organizer of Southwest University.
西南大学的筹办员了
Then everyone will be out of trouble.
那样大家都没有麻烦了
Besides, after arriving in Shanghai
另外 到上海以后
Put this issue of mine
我把这一期的
New Youth is compiled first.
《新青年》先编好
We'll discuss the later things.
后面的事情我们再商量
This can be the safest way at present.
可以 这是目前最稳妥的办法
inspector general
总监
Our people just went to Jiangan Hutong again.
我们的人刚才又去了趟箭杆胡同
陈独秀不在家
陈独秀不在家
Said he was looking for a friend to drink.
说是找朋友喝酒去了
I went drinking.
喝酒去了
Who did you go drinking with?
跟谁喝酒去了
Don't be a moth.
别是出什么幺蛾子吧
yes
是啊
Just arrest him.
给他抓起来算了
Come back, come back.
回来 回来 回来
You do things by yourself.
你这个人做事情啊
It's just a rush.
就是操之过急
You don't want to think about what time it is.
你也不想想现在是什么时候
North-South Peace Period
南北议和时期
I heard that Chen Jiongming even asked him out.
我听说陈炯明还约了他
Being the organizer of Southwest University?
做西南大学的筹办员呢
If we act rashly at this time
如果我们在这个时候贸然行事
Arrest him.
把他抓了
Can the southern government promise?
那南方政府能答应吗
Director!
总监啊
Chinese New Year is coming soon.
马上就要过年了
Chen Duxiu is a big hidden danger of public security in Beijing.
陈独秀可是京城治安的一大隐患
Look at his speech in Wuhan.
您看他在武汉的演讲
Intense and dynamic.
又激烈又有煽动性
This is devastating.
这破坏力可不得了啊
I know this, I know this.
这我知道 这我知道
You know what?
这样吧
Send someone to invite him to the hall tomorrow.
明天派人把他约到厅里来
Ask him to write a guarantee.
让他写份保证书
If he agrees to our terms
如果他答应我们的条件
Then let him go back.
那就放他回去
If he doesn't agree, then detain him.
如果他不答应 那就把他扣下
It's easy to tell the outside world.
这对外也好说啊
tomorrow
明天
got it
知道了
I'll arrange it
我去安排
good
好
Zhongfu
仲甫
Sister-in-law is here
嫂子来了
Where are you all?
你们都在呢
Zhongfu
仲甫
The police went to the house to look for you just now.
刚才警察又到家里找你去了
I told them
我跟他们说
You went to a friend's place for a drink.
你到朋友那儿喝酒去了
They left without saying anything.
他们没说什么就走了
But I'm worried about these cops.
但是我担心这帮警察
I'll meet you at home later.
一会儿还会到家里去找你
I think you should go out and hide now.
我觉得你现在就出去躲躲吧
Sure enough.
这果然
Sister-in-law, don't worry.
嫂子 您别着急
Brother Zhongfu is staying with us tonight.
今天晚上仲甫兄就住我们这儿
I trust him, Wu Bingxiang.
我谅他吴炳湘
You won't come to me to arrest people.
也不会跑到我这儿来抓人
Brother Shizhi Zhongfu can't stay with you.
适之 仲甫兄不能住在你这儿
You are also one of the sponsors.
你也是保人之一
Wu Bingxiang is likely to come here to arrest people.
吴炳湘很有可能上你这儿来抓人
I suggest going to my place to hide tonight.
我建议 今天晚上去我那儿躲躲
Besides, you can't take the train tomorrow.
另外明天你也不能坐火车
Depart from Beijing to Shanghai
从北京出发去上海
Because the police have already killed you
因为警察已经把你死了
They won't let you go.
他们不会让你走的
I'll see you off.
由我来送你
How about we start from Tianjin?
我们从天津出发 怎么样
good
好
Leave without delay.
事不宜迟 马上动身
中富兄
仲甫兄
Today's farewell
今日一别
I don't know when I will see you again.
不知何时才能再见
Wait for me. I'll get the wine.
等我一下 我去拿酒
Zhoudiaojiu
花周雕酒
The kind you drank.
你喝过的那种
Deqian is too late.
德潜 来不及了
I can run there in time.
来得及 我跑着去
Deqian
德潜
I have flower carvings here.
我这儿有花雕
Yeah, yeah, carved wine
对对对 花雕酒
Carved wine can't be cold.
花雕酒不能喝凉的
Bad for health.
对身体不好
I'll heat it up.
我去热一下
Siblings don't have to
弟妹 不用
Wine is cold and heart is hot.
酒是凉的心是热的
come on
来吧
come
来
Guys!
各位兄弟
I arrived in Beijing at the beginning of the Republic of China.
民国六年初我到的北京
I wanted to.
本来是想
Help Cai Yuanpei for three months
帮蔡元培三个月的忙
I didn't expect this one thousand for three years.
没想到这一干就整整三年
These three years
这三年
I ran New Youth by myself.
我丛单打独斗办《新青年》
Gathered so many fellow brothers.
到聚集了这么多的同人兄弟
Start a career.
开创了一个事业
Set up a banner.
树起了一杆大旗
I have a clear conscience and am very content.
我问心无愧 也非常知足
This cup of wine
这杯酒
I respect my brothers' love for me.
我敬各位兄弟对我的厚爱
Jun, you also accompany me.
君曼 你也陪着
Brother Zhongfu, remember a few years ago
仲甫兄 还记得几年前
Do you know each other in Taoranting?
你我在陶然亭相识吗
How can I forget that?
那哪能忘啊
You warmed up the wine at home
你在家把酒热好了
Afraid of being cold and wrapped in a quilt
怕凉 用棉被裹着
Rent a rickshaw to Tao Ranheng.
租一黄包车送到陶然亨
Long snow and ice
大雪漫漫 冰天雪地
But we are drinking hot carved wine.
我们却喝着滚烫的花雕酒
This is also unprecedented and unprecedented.
这也算是前无古人 后无来者了
This wine is a little cold today.
今天这酒它有些凉
Brother Zhongfu, I used my hands for a while.
仲甫兄 我用手焐了一会儿
You change my bowl.
你换我这碗
That's it.
这样就好了
So inside my chest
这样我胸膛里面
You can burn a fire.
就可以燃烧了一团火
You have snow and carved flowers.
有你 有雪 有花雕
Isn't this the same as that day?
这不跟那天一样吗
the same as
一样 一样
carry sth through to the end
有始有终
Brother Zhongfu, you are my forever friend.
仲甫兄 你是我永远的朋友
中富兄
仲甫兄
I really have to thank you.
我真的得好好感谢你啊
Can make me
能够让我成为
Peer editor of New Youth magazine
《新青年》杂志的同人编辑
This is what I have gained the most.
这是我收获最大
The most fulfilling period of feeling.
感觉最充实的一段时期
I should be the one to say thank you.
该说谢谢的应该是我
Since our "New Youth"
自从我们 《新青年》
Since the implementation of peer editing
实行同人编辑以来
Yi Han wrote a large number of books.
一涵撰写了数量众多
An extremely heavy article
分量极重的文章
You are a scientific and democratic idea.
你是科学与民主理念
One of the most active propagandists
最积极的宣传者之一
It's also our New Youth.
也是我们《新青年》
A worthy hero
当之无愧的功臣
Laigan
来 干
speak one's mind
说心里话
No Chen Duxiu forced Zhou Shuren.
没有陈独秀逼周树人
There is no Diary of a Madman.
就没有《狂人日记》
And Kong Yiji.
和《孔乙己》
There is no such person named Lu Xun.
也没有这个叫鲁迅的人
Brother Zhongfu, I really thank you.
仲甫兄 我真的谢谢你
Yucai, I always thought
豫才 我从来就认为
You are the most profound novelist in China.
你是中国思想最深刻的小说家
You have to fight the banner of new culture.
新文化的大旗得你来打
Lu Xun is the real standard bearer.
鲁迅才是真正的旗手
Brother Zhongfu, time waits for no man.
仲甫兄 时间不等人哪
good
好
Go like this.
就这样 走
Don't send either.
都不送
Brother Zhongfu, this is going south.
仲甫兄 这趟去南方
What are you going to do? I want to know
你打算怎么做 我想知道
I was going to ask you the same question.
我也正想问你这个问题呢
You said you planned to go to Peking University.
你说你打算在北大
Publicize Marxism with great fanfare
大张旗鼓地宣传马克思主义
I'm also going to engage in a workers' movement in Changxindian.
还准备在长辛店搞工人运动
Tell me what you think.
你到底怎么设想的 说给我听听
I'm going to open a few courses first.
我打算先开几门课
Socialism and social movements
社会主义和社会运动
historical materialism
唯物史观
International movement of workers
工人的国际运动
And the future of socialism.
和社会主义的将来
Besides, I plan to stay in Peking University.
另外我打算在北京大学
Run a Marxist theory research society.
办一个马克思学说研究会
I also discussed it with Zhongxia.
跟中夏也商量过了
I want to go to Changxindian to run night classes for workers.
想去长辛店办工人夜校
Organize workers' movement
组织工人运动
Organize workers' club
筹办工人俱乐部
I think this May Fourth Movement
我觉得这次五四运动
The reason why we were able to win
之所以能够胜利
A very important one.
很重要的一条
That is, the working class in Shanghai has risen.
就是上海的工人阶级都起来了
right
对
I said that the political environment in Shanghai is better than that in Beijing.
我说上海比北京的政治环境好
It refers to this.
指的就是这个
According to Marx's theory
依照马克思的理论
The class is the advanced representative of productive forces.
工人阶级是生产力的先进代表
Should be the leading class of the revolutionary movement.
应该是革命运动的领导阶级
be
是
Shouchang, what you said is a process.
守常 你说的这些都是过程
Have you thought about it?
你想过没有
What is our self-label?
我们的自标是什么
Why do we leave our wives behind?
我们为什么要抛妇别雏
Abandon one's family business and hide in hiding.
抛家舍业 东躲西藏
You may even lose your life.
甚至会丢掉身家性命
What are we after?
我们到底在追求什么
Mom, I'll help you.
妈妈 我帮你
good
好
I'll slow down.
一二三 我慢点啊
Go forward.
走 往前
Slow, slow, slow, slow
慢点 慢点慢点慢点
What are you doing?
你们干什么
Why did you come in without saying hello?
怎么不打个招呼就进来了
Hello, Jenny
师母 您好
Is Mr. Wang back?
先生回来了吗
He's not here.
他不在
Where have you been?
上哪儿去了
I don't know.
我不知道
Where are you going?
您这是要去哪儿啊
Clean up the bad things I don't use at home.
我收拾家里不用的坏东西
Throw it out.
扔出去
not have
没有
wife of one's teacher/master
师母
If sir comes back
如果先生回来
Please ask him to go to the Metropolitan Police Department.
务必请他到京师警察厅去一趟
Have something important to discuss.
有要事相商
Thank you for your cooperation.
多谢您的配合
The box is a little heavy.
箱子有点沉
turn around
向后转
quick march
齐步走
Zimei
子美
mother
妈妈
english-english
英英
Ying Ying is back.
英英回来了
get down
下来
Come down quickly!
快下来
Ying Ying, come down.
英英 下来
Ying Ying, come down!
英英 快下来
In fact, in recent days
其实最近几天
I've been thinking about drinking in your house.
我一直在想在你们家喝酒的时候
Shizhi asked me that sentence.
适之问我的那句话
He said that we are all Lyu3 bu4.
他说咱们都已经是人中吕布
Ma Chi rabbit has been killed.
马中赤兔了
Why abandon your wife and children?
为什么要抛妻弃子
What exactly do we want?
我们究竟想要什么
Brother Zhongfu, I also want to ask you
仲甫兄 我也想问你
Have you made this problem clear?
这个问题你搞清楚了吗
I think I've figured it out.
我想我已经想明白了
I think I figured it out, too.
我觉得我也想明白了
Our country
咱们这个国家
It has created the greatest number of people
曾经创造过人类历史上
The most splendid civilization
最灿烂的文明
But after the Opium War?
可是鸦片战争之后呢
Our country is sinking rapidly.
咱们这个国家迅速沉论
unknown
闻所未闻
But in 80 years.
不过八十年的时间
Our country
咱们这个国家
Has become the poorest in the world.
就已经变成了世界上最贫穷
The country with the least dignity
最没有尊严的国家
Warlords and bandits are rampant.
军阀混战 盗匪横行
People are displaced.
百姓流离失所
Live a miserable life.
过着水深火热的日子
What about us?
我们呢
Is one of the few intellectuals in this country.
是这个国家为数不多的文化人
A literate person is a civilized person.
文化人就是文明人
Civilized people should
文明人就应该
Be responsible for our country and people.
为我们的国家和人民负责
We have the responsibility to lead the people in their struggle.
我们有责任带领人民进行抗争
We're going to use what Marx created
我们要用马克思创立的
Principles of scientific socialism
科学社会主义原理
We should build a system of not being bullied by foreigners.
我们要建立不被外国人欺负
Not oppressed by rulers
不受统治者压迫
There is no corrupt official.
没有贪官污更
Everyone can be the master.
人人能够当家做主
Everyone can live in
人人都能生活在
A beautiful society with equal life.
幸福平等生活的美好社会
Brother Zhongfu, I think this is history.
仲甫兄 我觉得这是历史
Our responsibilities and responsibilities
赋予我们的责任和担当
None of us can let it down.
我们谁都不能把它辜负了
寿昌说得好
守常 说得好
But what are we going to rely on?
可是我们到底要靠什么
To fulfill this responsibility and responsibility.
来完成这份责任和担当
organization
组织
We should have one.
我们应该要有一个
An organization and leadership core that can gather strength.
能够凝聚力量的组织和领导核心
Brother Zhongfu, I think this matter
仲甫兄 我觉得这件事
It should be on the agenda.
应该提上议程了
This matter is too important.
这件事情太重要了
I need you to make a good plan
你我要好好地筹划一下
What did you say?
你说什么
People disappeared overnight.
这一夜之间人就没了
Is there really a moth?
真出幺蛾子了
Subordinate analysis
属下分析
Chen Duxiu must be hiding in someone's house.
陈独秀一定躲在谁的家里
Ready to sneak out of Beijing.
准备伺机溜出北京
You mean he hasn't left yet?
你的意思是说 他还没有走啊
It snowed so heavily.
下那么大的雪
How did he get out of town alone?
他一个人怎么出城
impossible
不可能
I suggest
我建议
Let's add hidden posts at Qianmen Railway Station.
咱们在前门火车站增加暗岗
He is likely to escape by train.
他很有可能坐火车出逃
You know what?
你这样吧
Take my film.
拿上我的片子
Give me Hu Shi, please
把胡适给我请来
I'm going to ask him as a sponsor.
我要向他这个保人要人
be
是
Two gentlemen
二位先生
Look, you are learned people.
看你们就是有学问的人
Have pity on me.
可怜可怜我这
Starving granddaughter, right?
快要饿死的小孙女吧
You sound like you're from the south.
听您口音像是从南边过来的
Fengyang, Anhui
安徽凤阳的
Fengyang
凤阳
Fengyang is a good place.
凤阳是好地方啊
A thousand walks are worse than two banks of Huaihe River.
走千走万 不如淮河两岸
How can there be famine this year?
怎么今年 也闹灾荒
Make a famine
闹灾荒
Plague
闹瘟疫
Make bandits
闹土匪
Make a fuss.
闹兵乱
You can't live with anything.
啥都闹 没法活了
And escaped.
就逃出来了
old man
老爷子
This winter's
这大冬天的
Why don't you go south?
怎么不往南边去呀
Originally, our family
本来我们一家人
Want to go to Jinan to go to relatives
想去济南投奔亲戚
I didn't expect to fight all the way.
可没想到一路都在打仗
There are refugees everywhere.
到处都是难民
Relatives were not found.
亲戚没找着
This followed the big slip to Tianjin Wei.
这就顺着大溜来到了天津卫
Are all the refugees from Anhui?
这难民都是从安徽来的吗
There are everywhere.
哪儿的都有
Shanxi, Henan
河南 山东 山西
Hebei
河北 安徽的
Shandong is in great trouble this year.
山东今年闹大灾
The most people came out to escape.
出来逃荒人最多
You take it.
您拿着来
It's no use giving it to me.
你给我这也没有用啊
Do you have anything to eat?
有吃的吗
Keep it. It will work.
您收着吧 能管用
Good man?
好人哪
Children, give them their heads.
孩子 快给他们磕头
This is a benefactor.
这是恩人哪
No, no, no
不用 不用 不用
Good man?
好人哪
Thank you benefactor
谢谢恩人
Wife, son
老伴儿啊 儿子啊
I brought you a boat.
我给你们送船来了
You go over there.
你们到那边
Don't freeze, don't be hungry.
别冻着 别饿着呀
There is a habit of lighting rivers in the north.
北方有放河灯的习惯
Pay homage to the dead
祭奠亡灵
old man
老爷子
You light so many lights!
您点这么多的灯啊
There are many friends and brothers over there.
那边的朋友兄弟多
I can't leave them alone.
我不能让他们孤单哪
You are paying homage to a friend.
您这是 祭奠朋友
It was the Boxer Rebellion that year.
都是当年闹义和团
A brother who risked his life.
一起出生入死的弟兄
I've been dead for twenty years.
死了小二十年了
They were killed by foreigners for their country.
他们是为国家被洋人杀死的
At the time of death
死的时候
Everyone is a lively little ye.
个个都是活蹦乱跳的小爷
My daughter-in-law left without marrying.
媳妇没娶就走了
I'm the only one left
只剩我一个人
I can't leave it alone.
我不能不管哪
They died for their country.
他们是为国捐躯而死的
It's worth dying for
死得值啊
Worth a fart
值个屁
I'll send them lights today.
我今天来给他们送灯
Is to give them cry foul.
就是给他们喊冤叫屈
Die for a country like this.
为这样的国家去死
It's a sucker
是冤大头
Look at this river bank.
你看看这满河堤上
Over the years.
这么多年来
One hundred and sixty days a year
一年三百六十天
Which day is not full of victims?
哪天不是满满当当的灾民哪
Starving to death, freezing to death, dying of illness
饿死的冻死的 病死的
Throw it on the side of the road and no one will bury it.
扔在路边没人埋
You are white flour scholars.
您二位是白面书生
I just want to ask.
我就问一句
Can such a country still be saved?
这样的国家还有救吗
Doesn't the government care?
政府难道不管吗
government
政府
I've never seen such an asshole government.
哪见过这么浑蛋的政府
When did they care?
他们什么时候关心过
The lives of ordinary people!
老百姓的死活呀
When Eight-Nation Alliance came in.
八国联军杀进来的时候
This Haihe River floats everywhere.
这海河上到处漂的
Are the heads of Chinese households.
都是中国人的户首
Some lost their heads.
有的没了头
Some limbs are incomplete.
有的四肢不全
Some women are naked.
有的女子光着身子
Kena
可怜哪
Common people's hardships
老百姓命苦
Get used to it for so many years.
这么多年 习惯了
Shouchang
守常
i figured it out
我想通了
We have to build a party.
我们得建党
We have to have a strong leadership core.
我们得有一个坚强的领导核心
What kind of party do you want to build?
你想建一个什么样的党
One uses Marx's theory
一个用马克思学说
Armed advanced political parties
武装起来的先进政党
One can lead China to the light.
一个可以把中国引向光明
Let Chinese people live a good life.
让中国人能够过上好日子的
Proletarian political party
无产阶级的政党
Why did you build this political party?
你为什么要建这个政党
No reason
不为什么
I did it for them.
我为了他们
Be able to live like a human being.
能够像人一样地活着
In order that they can have human rights.
为了他们能够拥有人的权利
People's happiness
人的快乐
Human dignity
人的尊严
好中富兄
好 仲甫兄
Let's swear to these compatriots.
让我们对着这些同胞宣誓吧
come
来
Let's announce
让我们宣誓
To keep you from being displaced.
为了让你们不再流离失所
In order to let the Chinese people
为了让中国的老百姓
Live a rich and happy life
过上富裕幸福的生活
To stop the poor from being bullied.
为了让穷人不再受欺负
Everyone can be the master.
人人都能当家做主
For everyone to be educated.
为了人人都受教育
There is little to teach and old to depend on.
少有所教 老有所依
For the Chinese people's prosperity and national strength.
为了中华民富国强
For national reconstruction and rejuvenation
为了民族再造复兴
I am willing to fight all my life.
我愿意奋斗终生
Organization, known in history as South Chen Bei Li made an appointment to found the party.
[1920年2月，李大钊冒险将受到警察捕的陈独秀送出北京。路上，两人约定，分别在北京和上海等地筹建党的组织，史称南陈北李相约建党。]
Brother Shizhi, please sit down.
适之兄 请坐吧
Sit down.
坐吧
This Chen Duxiu has left Beijing.
这个陈独秀已经离开北京了
I left that night.
当天晚上就走了
How did he die?
他是怎么走的
I'm not sure how to go.
怎么走的我不大清楚
Half a moment!
稍等
He left a letter for you.
他留了一封信给您
Director Wu
吴总监
In the summer, I am grateful for the preferential treatment.
夏间备承优待 至为感佩
I received a telegram from a friend here a few days ago.
日前接此间友人电促
Come to discuss with Southwest University.
前来面商西南大学事宜
Departure is not enough to report to the hall.
匆匆启行 未及报厅
I'm sorry
颇感歉仄
Hereby, I am writing to supplement you.
特此专函补陈
Hope for the original
希为原有
Go back to Beijing as soon as you can.
事了即行回京
Thank you for your face again
再为面谢
Please honor Chen Duxiu.
敬请勋安 陈独秀
This Chen Duxiu is interesting
这个陈独秀有点意思啊
deserve the name of a true friend
够朋友
He's a sponsor for both of us.
他这是为咱们两个保人
Unload the responsibility
卸责任哪
Zhongfu, he has always been a man who values love and righteousness.
仲甫他一直是一个重情重义的人
He also said
他还说了
In two days, let the southern government
过两天就让南方政府
Write a special official letter to you.
专门开一份公函给你
In this case, you will be completely irresponsible.
这样的话 你就彻底没有责任了
Ok, it's going to rain, and my mother is going to get married.
行吧 天要下雨娘要嫁人
Suck It Up
随它去吧
Do you know
你知道吗
I don't think you can compare Shanghai with Beijing
我认为你无法比较上海和北京
I don't think you can compare it.
我认为你比较不出来
They are so different.
它们是如此地不同
Just like Beijing.
就像北京
There is a sandstorm
有沙尘暴
I can't cope with it
我无法应对它
I really can't cope.
我真的无法应对
Unable to cope with sandstorm
无法应对沙尘暴
There will be rain in Shanghai.
上海会有下雨的时候
Sometimes it's wet.
也有潮湿的时候
But to be honest, I really don't like Shanghai.
但老实说 我实在不太喜欢上海
But Beijing
但是北京
Honestly, I can live there.
老实说我可以居住在那里
Because of the difference in weather
因为天气差异的原因
I think it is more
我觉得比较
Differences between Beijing and Shanghai
北京和上海之间的差异
Still very interesting.
还是非常有趣的
I mean
我的意思是
This is a different kind of comparison.
这是一种不同的比较
It's like comparing night with day.
就像比较黑夜和白天一样
Thank you very much.
非常感谢你
The relationship between them is really important.
它们之间的关系真的很重要
寿昌先生
守常先生
I'll go first if you are busy.
您先忙着 我就先走了
Please walk slowly.
您慢走
寿昌先生
守常先生
Runzhi
润之
I lost weight, too.
也瘦了
But more energetic.
但是更精神了
nicely
好 好
sir
先生
Thanks to Jenny's two cans of Chili oil
多亏了师母的两罐辣椒油啊
Just in time
来得及时
Otherwise, I may not be able to stand it.
要不然我都不一定顶得过来
I'll ask her to make more for you.
我让她再给你多做点儿
Put more chili.
多放点儿辣椒
Get it
要得 要得
Give me
给我
Sit, sit
坐 坐 坐
来润之
来润之
sit
坐
Give me a minute.
等我一下啊
润之啊
润之啊
How's the Zhang-expelling movement going in Hunan?
这个湖南的驱张运动搞得怎么样了
Tell me about it quickly.
赶紧跟我说说啊